This lecture is Introduction to
Facilitated Positional Release.
Our session objectives
are posted there on the
slide. We're going to talk
about the history of FPR.
We'll explain the
principles of FPR, the
physiology, physiologic
mechanisms involved.
I'll talk about some indications
and contraindications
of the FPR technique
and explain how to
apply the principles of
FPR to treat any given
traumatic dysfunction
based on your knowledge of
anatomy and the function
of the given region.
FPR, or Facilitated
Physitional Release,
was developed by Dr.
Stanley Shiawitz.
He was the dean of
NYITCOM, or when he
was dean it was NICOM,
from 1991 to 2002.
The story goes that
90 seconds was too
long for Dr. Shiawicz
to do Counterstrain.
He had a very busy
practice, and he had
to do everything as
quickly as possible.
So he developed Facilitated
Positional Release,
and the students and
fellows he was working
with at the time didn't
know what to call it,
so they used to document
on the chart I.O.,
And when Dr. Scheiwitz
saw IO, he had
asked them, what
does IO stand for?
And they said it's
instant osteopathy.
So he figured they needed
a better name than that.
So they eventually came up
with facilitated positional
release. But that's a
little back story on FPR.
FPR is a passive,
indirect technique.
It's suggested that FPR
uses the muscle spindle
reflex. The theory is that
compressing the muscles
past their neutral position
results in a quieting
of the gamma motor gain
to the muscle spindle and
this leads to a resetting
of the tension and
resetting of the hypertonicity
of the muscle fibers.
So what are the basics
of performing FPR?
First you want to neutralize
the position of
the dysfunction.
Then you want to
add a facilitating
force to the point
being treated
and a facilitating
point force can be
either compression,
traction, or torque.
You want to maintain that
facilitating force and
guide the dysfunction
into its freedoms and hold
it in that position for
three to five seconds.
Then you release
the facilitating
force and guide the
dysfunction back to
the baseline position
and reassess.
Now we're going to
talk a little bit about
indications and
contraindications of FPR.
Well, basically, any
condition where a
somatic dysfunction is
present is an indication
for facilitated
positional release.
Something to note is you
might want to treat the
larger muscle groups
first before treating the
joints, and this goes along
with what you might do
with other techniques as
well. If the paraspinal
muscles are really tight,
you're going to want to
treat those muscles before
you get down into the
individual thoracic or
lumbar or cervical segments.
So for example, someone with
neck pain due to whiplash,
you'll treat that cervical
soft tissue first and then
move on to the individual
cervical spinal segments.
So what are some
contraindications of FPR?
Well, if a patient's
not able to
tolerate treatment
position, you're not
going to perform
FPR on this patient.
Or what you might be
able to do is modify
your technique to perform
FPR, but maybe not
necessarily the way
you originally intended
to do it, or use a
different technique.
If somebody can't tolerate
compression, maybe
you can add a little
traction. Something
like that would be how
you would modify it.
If a patient has radicular
pain when performing to the
cervical spine using
compression, similar to when
you're doing a spiraling
maneuver, you're not going to
want to do FPR using compression
in the cervical spine.
So what do you do? Maybe
reposition, try it with
traction like I said earlier,
or try another technique.
Another contraindication
would be if the patient
has any condition in
the region being treated
where an introduction
of torque, traction,
or compression is
contraindicated, or also the
treatment position if
it's contraindicated. For
instance, hip replacement.
You don't want to,
if somebody had a hip
replacement, the treatment
position for treating
a herniated disc might
not be able to be
performed for this patient.
Someone with shoulder
pathology, the
treatment position for
rib one, for example,
might not be tolerated
by the patient. A patient
who has chronic shoulder
dislocation or separation,
any treatment that moves or
puts force into the shoulder
might not be tolerated
by the patient or could
possibly dislocate the
shoulder again. So you're not
going to perform the
technique if that's the case.
Any recent trauma,
fracture, or dislocation
at the area involved
with the treatment
would be a contraindication
of doing FPR.
Also, you would want to use
caution in osteoporosis.
If there's a malignancy,
you know, osteoporosis or
malignancy, maybe putting
compression could possibly give
a compression fracture.
So you want to be careful.
You shouldn't be putting
that much pressure,
that much compression
into an area.
Even with someone
with osteoporosis, you
should be able to
tolerate it, but it's
a caution, so you
have to be careful.
Certain rheumatologic
disorders, if the treatment
position involves a
position that the patient
can't tolerate, you want
to be careful. If there
are any congenital
malformations, the same thing.
If somebody has stenosis,
again, depending on what
you're doing, you may be
exacerbating the pain.
And, of course, always use
your clinical judgment for
any disease that the patient
has. If you think that
it's contraindicated, then
do something different.
Side effects of FPR
are similar to most
manipulative techniques,
and they are transient.
Fatigue, soreness,
stiffness. and this is
usually primarily due to
the restoration of the
circulation to the
previously dysfunctional area
and the release of
muscular waste products.
Let's go through a case.
A 29-year-old male with no
significant past medical
history presents to
your office complaining
of achy low back pain for
10 years. He was a gymnast
in high school and has
had pain intermittently
since then. When his back
goes out, the severity
of the pain is a sharp
8 out of 10. On a normal
day, it is a 4 out of 10
at the end of the day.
Nothing really makes
it better or worse.
The pain is non
-radiating. He has no
associated numbness,
tingling, weakness,
or bowel or bladder
function changes.
He brought in to his
visit a recent lumbosacral
spine x-ray and an MRI
which showed some mild
degenerative changes but
nothing else of significance.
He has had some childhood
asthma, no surgeries,
he denies alcohol,
drug, or tobacco use.
His family history,
both parents and his
siblings, two siblings
are alive and well
and the review systems is only
positive for the back pain.
On physical exam,
his lower extremity
motor is 5 out
of 5 bilaterally.
L4 and S1 reflexes are 2
out of 4 bilaterally. He has
no gross sensory deficit in
his lower extremities. He
has a negative straight
leg raise bilaterally, and
he has no costovertebral
angle tenderness bilaterally.
He has a negative Faber
test. You find paravertebral
muscle spasm bilaterally.
He has bilateral
psoas spasm. He has
bilateral hamstring spasm.
You note a right quadratus
lumborum spasm, and you
also find L5 extended
rotated side vent right.
Your assessments are low
back pain, muscle spasm,
somatic dysfunction
in the lumbar region,
and somatic dysfunction
in the lower extremity.
So what are we
going to do here?
For his low back pain, we
can give him some hamstrings,
psoas, quadratus lumborum,
and paraspinal muscle
stretches. Tell them to
do them twice a day. I
like to tell the patients
to do three sets of 20
-second stretching split up
with a few seconds of resting
in between for a total of
one minute of stretching.
You always tell them
to do both sides so the
patient would do both
hamstrings, both psoases, etc.
And I usually like to tell
them to do it twice a day.
For the muscle spasm,
you're doing the same thing.
It all goes together, so the
stretches go with
the low back pain.
For the somatic dysfunctions,
in the lumbar region,
you're going to do some
soft tissue, some muscle
energy, and some facilitated
positional release.
For his lower extremity, you
can do some muscle energy.
Right now, you're
probably asking yourself,
how do we treat the
L5 ERS right with FPR?
I'm glad you were asking
that because basically
what you do is you
neutralize the region,
you compress, that's
your facilitating force,
you put the dysfunction
into its freedoms,
and then you basically
take them out
of that and reassess.
I'll talk about
it step by step.
For neutralizing,
you place the dysfunction,
take it out of extension, make
sure it's not an extension,
not inflection, make
sure it's not rotated or
side bent in any direction.
That's your neutralization.
Then you add a compressive
force. So in this case, you
would be compressing down.
If the patient's seated,
what you would do is
you would compress down
from the shoulders to
the L5 dysfunction.
And you're putting just
enough pressure so that you
can feel the compression
at your monitoring finger.
Then maintaining
that compression,
you're going to gently extend,
rotate right, and sidebend
right, just until you feel
motion at L5. So remember,
when you're at neutral,
any degree off of zero
is going to be flexion or
extension or rotation or
sidebending. So you don't need
much once you're at neutral,
so just keep that in
mind. So you're going to
gently guide the dysfunction
into its freedoms and wait
three to five seconds.
After three to five
seconds, you can take the
compression off and just
bring the patient back to
a regular seated position
or a regular starting
position, whatever it
might have been. In this
case, we said the patient
was sitting down, but
if the patient's lying
down and you're treating
the neck, you put the neck,
put the head back down
on the table in a natural
position at the end.
And then you reassess.
So that's pretty much it.
You remember, for the most
part, what we do, when we
do FPR, we're doing
compression. So if you remember,
neutralize, compress, freedoms,
and then reassess, you'll
have a good idea of what
to do when you're treating
something with FPR. If you
don't know the position to
put it in because you didn't
learn it, just neutralize,
compress, move it to the
freedoms, and you have it.
To summarize,
FPR is a passive,
indirect technique.
We utilize the muscle
spindle, and the way to do
it is to neutralize, add
your facilitating force,
guide it to its freedoms,
return to baseline,
and reassess. So
it's neutralize,
compress, freedoms,
return to baseline,
reassess. And if you don't
like compression,
you can always add
traction, and some techniques
you'll learn a little
bit of a torque as a
facilitating force.
That's it. Please don't
forget to do the evaluation.
Go to the link at the
end of this PowerPoint
and do the evaluation.
Thank you very much.